Finding Aid for Dept. of Geography (University of Michigan) records, 1925-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Geography (University of Michigan) records 1925-1982
University of Michigan. Dept. of Geography.
2.2 linear feet
87148 Bimu C26 2
The Department of Geography Records include personal and professional papers of departmental chairmen, Kenneth C. McMurry and Charles Davis; also administrative papers, including minutes of faculty meetings, curriculum plans, correspondence, and memos and agendas; and papers relating to Chi Gamma Phi, geography honor society, and the Quadrangle Club.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor no. 6794 ) came to the library in June 1982. Originally four feet, the collection included published materials, student records, routine departmental correspondence, duplicates, and some files of Professors Charles David and Kenneth McMurry of minimal informational value. These files have been removed and returned to the donor.
The collection is open to research.
The first geography courses taught at the University of Michigan were offered through the Department of Geology. The size and importance of the geography curriculum within the Department of Geology increased and in 1915/1916 the department was renamed the Department of Geology and Geography. In 1923, the instruction of geography was organized into a separate department and Assistant Professor Kenneth C. McMurry was named to oversee the administration of the new department. Professor McMurry was chairman of the Department of geography until 1955/1956. Professor Charles "Bud" Davis succeeded Professor McMurry and held the position of chairman until 1965/1966. From then until the dissolution of the department in 1982, four different professors acted as chairman: L.A.P. Gosling, 1966-1968 and 1971-1974; M.G. Marcus, 1969-1971; D.R. Deskins, 1974-1979; and J.D. Nystuen, 1979-1982.
The Regents approved elimination of the Department of Geography in June 1981. According to Mr. Billy Frye, Vice-President of Academic Affairs, among the six major reasons for discontinuance were the general economic climate and the University's need to reduce expenditures; and deficiencies in overall department scholarly quality, productivity, and lack of centrality to the curriculum and intellectual life of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. In 1982, the Department of Geography had 13 members, nine tenured. The tenured members of the faculty were offered positions in other departments within the University.
The Department of Geography records consist of 6 series: Histories, Kenneth C. Murray, Charles M. Davis, Administrative Files, Topical Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Chi Gamma Phi.; Geography.; Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); Davis, Charles Moler, 1900-; McMurry, Kenneth Charles.
- Histories
  The Histories series contains several drafts of a historical narrative of the department, and one newspaper clipping.
  - History of the Department of Geography to 1971 (Box 1)
- Kenneth C. McMurry 1925-1939
  The next two series include the personal and professional papers of Professor Kenneth C. McMurry and Professor Charles "Bud" Davis during their tenure as chairman of the department, and of administrative files. Also included are papers documenting Chi Gamma Phi, a geography honor society, and papers relating to the Quadrangle Club of the University of Michigan.
  - Chi Gamma Phi 1929-1939
    - Constitution and Financial Reports (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Secretary's Reports (Box 1)
    - Report: The Description of a Proposed Geographical Study of the "Oaks Openings" Area of Northeastern Ohio and Southeastern Michigan (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1926-1939
    - Michigan Academy of Sciences (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - P.S. Lovejoy (Box 1)
  - Council on National Parks, Forests, and Wild Life (Box 1)
  - Emmett County Wilderness Park 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Isle Royale 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - McMurray Projects and Memos 1920-1927 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Economic Land Surveys 1925-1927 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Water Code 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Tax Land Conservation Projects 1936 (Box 1)
  - Waterloo Projects 1931 (Box 1)
- Charles M. Davis
  - Lecture Notes
    - Australia and New Zealand (Box 1)
    - North America (Box 1)
    - Pacific (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers, including bibliography (Box 1)
  - Publications not listed in bibliography (Box 1)
  - Quadrangle (Box 1)
- Administrative Files 1959-1981
  The Administrative Files, 1959-1981, include faculty meeting minutes, curriculum plans, correspondence, memos, and agendas.
  - Class Enrollment 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1959-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Credit Study 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum
    - Graduate Curriculum, pre-1970 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Curriculum 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Planning Committee 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Dean's Office Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Department Planning Committee 1972 (Box 2)
  - LSA Dean's Executive Committee
    - 1966/67-1968/69 (Box 2)
    - 1970/71-1971/72 (Box 2)
  - Memos and Agendas
    - 1966-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of Faculty Meetings
    - 1966/67-1967/68 (Box 2)
    - 1968/69-1969/70 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Faculty vitas 1981 (Box 2)
  - Research News, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Geography at Michigan Newsletter, 1969, August 1971 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files contain various subjects, including information on research projects, and computer programs at the University of Michigan.
  - Computer programs at Michigan (Box 2)
  - Departmental Research Projects, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Gamma Theta Upsilon (Box 2)
  - Innovating Teaching (Box 2)
  - Low Energy Living Proposal (Box 2)
  - Mountain High Seminar (Box 2)
  - Sponsored Research Projects (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series holds portraits of faculty and staff, including photos of individuals in their Angell Hall offices, as well as portraits of doctoral recipients, 1923-1970s.
  - Photographs (Box 3)